Simon Fraser University aerial and construction photograph collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University aerial and construction photograph collection
1963 - 1978
F-30
Q106644079
24 cm. of photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Archives and Records Management Department
The University Archives acquires, preserves and makes available three categories of materials: (1) the official records of the University, including those created by the Board of Governors, Senate, University committees, faculties, departments and administrative offices; (2) materials documenting the wider University community; and (3) historical research collections that promote the teaching and research activities of the University.
The Archives was established within the University Library in 1968 when librarian Liisa Fagerlund was appointed University Archivist on a half-time basis. She continued in this post until 1975 when she left the University. From 1975 to 1978, the Archives functioned within the Special Collections division of the Library. Archival duties were carried out by various library staff members. In 1978, the University Archives was established as a separate administrative unit outside of the Library. Donald Baird, recently retired as University Librarian, became University Archivist and held this position until his retirement in 1990. Jim Ross served as University Archivist from 1991 to 1993, and was succeeded by Ian Forsyth in 1994.
When the Archives was a function of the University Library, the University Archivist reported to the University Librarian. When the Archives was established as a separate administrative unit, the University Archivist reported directly to the University President. The reporting structure changed in 1986 when the University Archivist reported to the Vice-President, Research/Information Systems; in 1990, when the University Archivist reported to the Associate Vice-President, Academic; and in 1996, when the University Archivist reported to the Registrar/Dean of Students.
published
Full
Published
Title based on the contents of the collection.
The collection was compiled by the University Archives staff to illustrate the construction of Simon Fraser University.
The history of Simon Fraser University is reflected in its world-renowned architecture. Located atop Burnaby Mountain, SFU's design was the result of a competition held in 1963 by Dr. Gordon Shrum, the newly-appointed Chancellor of the University. The goal of the competition was to produce five winners. One architect would be awarded first prize for the overall design of SFU, while four other architects would each be invited to build a section of the University under the supervision of the winner. All entries were limited to applicants from British Columbia.
The informal guidelines for SFU's design consisted of a directive from Dr. Shrum entitled, "Notes from the Chancellor," which was distributed to the applicants. In this directive, Dr. Shrum noted many of the features that he felt were essential to the new university based upon his previous experience at the University of British Columbia. Among his recommendations were that students should be able to move from one part of the university to another without going outside, and that the large lecture theaters should be grouped together rather than scattered over the whole campus. Perhaps the most important of his criteria was that SFU should appear in 1965 essentially as it would look in 1995. In other words, it should look like a finished university, but also be designed for expansion. The design chosen was that of a young UBC architecture professor, Arthur Erickson, and his colleague Geoffrey Massey. The four other winners were William R. Rhone and Randle Iredale; Zoltan Kiss; Duncan McNab, Harry Lee, and David Logan; and Robert F. Harrison. The Erickson and Massey design had been the unanimous choice of the judges, and had met all the requirements that Shrum had outlined in his memo.
The collection consists of photographic prints and contact sheets that illustrate the physical development of SFU including site clearance, excavation, the construction of individual buildings, and completed buildings and interiors. There are a number of aerial photographs. The collection also includes photographs of the University's opening ceremonies and the installation of Dr. Shrum as Chancellor and Patrick McTaggart-Cowan as President.
The archivist grouped the collection into series according to photographer.
Archives and Records Management Department; Photographic materials; Records in electronic form (digitized); Buildings and structures
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals to the collection are expected.
The history of the collection is not known. Many of the prints were probably purchased by the University from freelance photographers who photographed the construction with a view towards selling copies of their work to SFU.
Please consult the inventory for the Department of Facilities Management (F-11) for textual records relating to the construction of SFU.
Access to the photographs is not restricted, but copyright restrictions do apply to this material. Please consult the archivist for details.
A file list is available.
- Herbert McDonald Photographs, 1963 - 1965; F-30-1; 6 cm of contact sheets
  published
  Series consists of contact sheets. The photographic subjects are: construction contract signing; aerial photographs showing the excavation and construction progress of SFU; the University's architectural design; the opening ceremonies; the first Board of Governors; a Presidential installation ceremony; and official portraits.
  McDonald, Herbert
  Access to the photographs is not restricted, but copyright restrictions do apply to this material. Please consult the archivist for details.
  - Architectural Design; Construction Contract Signing; 1st Board of Governers; and SFU site clearance, excavation, and construction progress photographs (numbers 1-25), 1963 - 1965; F-30-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-7)
    Textual records
    Open
  - SFU site clearance, excavation, and construction progress photographs (numbers 26-52), 1964 - 1965; F-30-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 30-7)
  - Opening Ceremonies photographs (numbers 1-4), 1965; F-30-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 30-7)
  - Official Portraits - Dr.McTaggart-Cowan; German Consul; Installation Ceremony - Dr.Gordon M.Shrum; and SFU construction progress photographs (numbers 1-7), 1964 - 1965; F-30-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 30-7)
- Leonard Frank Photographs, 1964 - 1967; F-30-2; 5 cm of photographs
  Series consists of photographs of construction progress of the Central Mall, the Science Complex, the Women's Residence, the Academic Quadrangle, and the Men's Residence.
  Frank, Leonard
  - Construction Progress - Central Mall (set 1-14), 1964 - 1965; F-30-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-3)
  - Construction Progress - Science Complex (set 1-12), 1964 - 1965; F-30-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 30-3)
  - Construction Progress - Academic Quadrangle (set 10-14), 1966; F-30-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 30-4)
  - Construction Progress - Women's Residence (set 1-4), 1965; F-30-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 30-4)
  - Construction Progress - Men's Residence (set 1-15), 1966 - 1967; F-30-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 30-4)
- George Allen Ltd. Photographs, 1963 - 1978; F-30-3; 6 cm of photographs
  Series consists of aerial shots of SFU site clearance, excavation and construction. Series also includes Installation Ceremony of Dr. Gordon M. Shrum.
  Allen, George; Photographic materials; Records in electronic form (digitized)
  - Aerial Photographs - SFU site clearance, excavation, and construction (numbers 9292-11801), 1963 - 1966; F-30-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-4)
    - 9292, 1963
      Photographic materials; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - 9328, 1964
    - 9613, 1964
    - 9614, 1964
    - 9758, 1964
    - 9948, 1964
    - 10349, 1964
    - 10358, 1964
    - 10519, 1964
    - 10526, 1964
    - 10605, 1965
    - 10886, 1965
    - 11061, 1965
    - 11062, 1965
      Photographic materials
    - 11159, 1965
    - 11462, 1965
    - 11620, 1965
    - 11622, 1965
    - 11623, 1965
    - 11625, 1965
    - 11627, 1965
    - 11628, 1965
    - 11801, [1965-1966]
  - Aerial Photographs - SFU site clearance, excavation, and construction (numbers 12120-14794), 1966 - 1968; F-30-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 30-5)
    - 12120, 1966
    - 12209, 1966
    - 12392, 1966
    - 12393, 1966
    - 12560, 1966
    - 12714, 1966
    - 12763, 1966
    - 12896, 1966
    - 13199, 1966
    - 13201, 1966
    - 13202, 1966
    - 13329, 1966
    - 13330, 1967
    - 13435, 1967
    - 13436, 1967
    - 13437, 1967
    - 13589, 1967
    - 13592, 1967
    - 13594, 1967
    - 14005, 1967
    - 14173, 1967
    - 14309, 1967
    - 14794, 1968
  - Aerial Photographs - SFU site clearance, excavation, and construction (numbers 15392-27590), 1968 - 1978; F-30-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 30-5)
    - 15391, 1968
    - 15392, 1968
    - 15393, 1968
    - 15926, 1969
    - 16423, 1969
    - 16424, 1969
    - 16714, 1969
    - 16718, 1969
    - 17116, 1970
    - 18166, 1971
    - 18167, 1971
    - 18168, 1971
    - 18336, 1971
    - 18720, 1972
    - 19053, 1972
    - 19873, 1973
    - 19875, 1973
    - 27590, 1978
  - Installation Ceremony - Shrum; McTaggart-Cowan (numbers 3035-3047), 1965; F-30-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 30-6)
    - 3035, 1965
    - 3036, 1965
    - 3037, 1965
    - 3038, 1965
    - 3039, 1965
    - 3040, 1965
    - 3041, 1965
    - 3042, 1965
    - 3043, 1965
    - 3044, 1965
    - 3046, 1965
    - 3047, 1965
  - Aerial photographs - colour, 1965 - 1966; F-30-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 30-6)
    - 5183, 1965 - 1966
    - Unnumbered colour print of SFU Burnaby - print 1, 1965 - 1966; aerial_unnumbered_1
    - Unnumbered colour print of SFU Burnaby - print 2, 1965 - 1966; aerial_unnumbered_2
- John Fulker Photographs, 1965; F-30-4; 19 photographs
  Series consists of photographs of SFU architecture including completed buildings and interior views.
  Fulker, John
  - SFU Architecture - photographic prints[19 black and white prints numbers 1, 2, 10, 13, 15-18, 21, 25, 27, 33, 60, 62, 63, 64 (two copies), 67], 1965; F-30-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-6)
- Herb Nott and Company Photographs, 1966; F-30-5; 2 photographs
  Series consists of photographs of SFU main mall.
  Nott, Herb
  - SFU Architecture - photographic prints(2 black and white prints numbers 219, 220), 1966; F-30-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-6)
- Rolly Ford Photograph, 1965; F-30-6; 1 photograph
  Series consists of a photograph of SFU swimming pool.
  Ford, Rolly
  - SFU Architecture - photographic print(1 black and white print number 191612), 1965; F-30-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-6)
- Miscellaneous Aerial Photographs, 1963 - 1969; F-30-7; 7 photographs
  Series consists of 7 aerial photographs of SFU by Lockwood Survey Corporation and others.
  - Miscellaneous aerial photographs, 1963 - 1969; F-30-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 30-6)